בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ג Nun Gimmel and
we are in the middle of discussing a different type of a
חזקה, chazakah, a חזקה chazakah more related to מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin
and מסכת בבא בתרא, Masechet Bava Batra, the חזקה chazakah of a
קנין. kinyan. Actually, we quoted yesterday a ברייתא baraita from the תוספתא
Tosefta of קידושין, Kiddushin, תני רב אושעיא בקידושין דבי לוי. Tani Rav
Oshaya be'Kiddushin d'Vei Levi. Okay, so this חזקה chazakah is not one
of the fields of contested and being brought as evidence; it's when
one of the specific concrete acts that you do to transfer ownership
by a field: כסף, kessef, שטר, shtar, חזקה. chazakah. כסף Kessef is
the buyer gives the money over, a שטר shtar is the seller
writes a שטר shtar that says, "I am selling my field to
you," and hands that שטר shtar over, and חזקה chazakah is that
the buyer goes and does some act on the land that demonstrates
his ownership of the land, and that has been defined right now
as נעל גדר ופרץ, na'al gadar u'paratz, which is some specific act
that right
now the way we're contrasting it against certainly it's not three years,
it's one specific concrete act, and it's not the eating of the
פירות peirot of the land, the benefiting from the land; it's actually
something that improves the land. You build up a wall, you make
an opening in a wall, you lock a gate, which we said
was a discussion whether you just lock it or whether you install
a lock. Okay,
something of that nature. So today's דף daf is really going to
be exploring exactly that. What are the exact parameters of what would
constitute this type of a חזקה? chazakah? So yesterday the גמרא Gemara
said, and maybe we can pick up from this
the following things: וכמה כלשהו? v'khama kol shehu? Let's pick up from
there again. It's like one, two, three, four, five, six lines down
from the top of נ"ג עמוד א'. Nun Gimmel Amud Aleph. So
it says if you do if you are נעל, na'al, you seal
the door, גדר, gadar, you make a wall, or פרץ, paratz, make
an opening even a small amount, that's a חזקה. chazakah. So how
much is a small amount?
כדיברי שמואל דאמר שמואל, kedivrei Shmuel d'amar Shmuel, Shmuel says גדר גדר
והשלימו לעשרה, gader geder vehishlimo l'asara,
if you made a wall that was already existing but you built
it up so now it's ten טפחים, tefachim, ופרץ פרצה כדי שיכנס
ויצא בה, u'paratz pirtza kedai sheyikanes ve'yetzei bah,
or you opened up an existing opening but makes it easier but
now you're able to go in and out, הרי זה חזקה, harei
zeh chazakah, that works. So now the גמרא Gemara wants to understand,
well, how much did you do? Because the way Shmuel describes it,
it sounded not like a כלשהו, kol shehu, it sounded like you
did something quite significant. So the גמרא Gemara says האי גדר היכי
דמי? hai geder heichi dami? What was the status of this wall
beforehand? אי אילמא דמעיקרא לא הוו סלקי לה, ee ileima d'meikara lo
havi salki lah, before you built up this extra amount people could
not go over it, it was high enough that people could not
go over
it, והשתא נמי לא סלקי לה, ve'hashta nami lo salki lah, and
you added to the height but it's still the same way it
always was, people could not go over it and now it's a
little taller and people can't go over it. Okay, so מאי עבד?
mai avad? So then it's not a כלשהו, kol shehu, you didn't
do anything substantial, you didn't make any practical difference. You made a
taller wall but it had no practical benefit. ואלא דמעיקרא הוו סלקי
לה, v'ela d'meikara havi salki lah, so let's say the opposite, before
it was because of its height people could go over it so
it really wasn't protecting the field, והשתא לא סלקי לה, ve'hashta lo
salki lah,
now because of what you added, people can't go over it, and
now it is protecting the field. טוב עבד! tuv avad! That's not
a כלשהו, kol shehu, that's a major change. So people could go
over it but with great difficulty. Well, you have now learned the
גמרא Gemara long enough that you anticipated the answer. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא צריכא דמעיקרא הוו סלקי לה בריווחא, lo tzericha d'meikara
havi salki lah be'rivcha, before
people could easily vault the wall, והשתא קא סלקי לה בדוחקא, ve'hashta
ka'salki lah be'duchka,
and now you've made it more hard for them. So you actually
have made a change, you've improved the wall, you've improved the protection
of the field, but you haven't gone from zero to a hundred,
right? You went from sixty to seventy, but you've improved the protection
of the field and therefore that's a כלשהו. kol shehu. But the
point is it has to accomplish something, okay? It can't be an
addition that really accomplishes nothing practical. So the גמרא Gemara is now
going to have the same question by the opening. האי פרצה היכי
דמי? hai pirtza heichi dami? How about the opening? What's the story?
אי אילמא דמעיקרא הוו עיילי בה, ee ileima d'meikara havi ayeili bah,
before the opening was big enough for people to go in and
out, it was totally functional, והשתא נמי עיילי בה, ve'hashta nami ayeili
bah, now you made it bigger but it hasn't added to the
functionality, so מאי עבד? mai avad? What good did you do? You
didn't do anything. ואלא דמעיקרא לא הוו עיילי בה, v'ela d'meikara lo
havi ayeili bah, it was too narrow that nobody could go into
it, והשתא עיילי בה, ve'hashta ayeili bah, now it's big enough that
it's actually usable. טוב עבד! tuv avad! So then it's not a
כלשהו, kol shehu, you made something from an unfunctional opening to a
functional opening. לא צריכא דמעיקרא הוו עיילי בה בדוחקא, lo tzericha d'meikara
havi ayeili bah be'duchka,
it was usable but it was a little narrow and
people it was hard to go in and out through it, והשתא
עיילי בה בריווחא, ve'hashta ayeili bah be'rivcha, and now you've made it
more comfortable. So therefore you have actually made an improvement. It doesn't
have to be a radical improvement, it could be that it's more
of a quantitative rather than a fully qualitative improvement, but it can't
be that it accomplished nothing. Okay. Why is the גמרא Gemara almost
repeating itself? Yeah, but we had two examples. We had a wall
and an opening. Yeah, exactly. The symmetry is beautiful. Right. So okay.
איתמר אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן: itamar amar Rav Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan: נתן צרור והועיל, natan tzeror veho'il, let's say you added
a rock to the wall and you made and you contributed, you
did something that benefited it. נטל צרור והועיל natal tzeror veho'il or
you took a rock out of the wall and that did something
that benefited it. הרי זו חזקה, harei zo chazakah, that's a חזקה.
chazakah. So the keyword here of course is הועיל, ho'il, meaning as
we've been saying before, it's not enough to just do something, you
have to do something meaningful. Okay now we want to understand what
is it exactly that you did here that was meaningful. מאי נתן
ומאי נטל? mai natan u-mai natal? What's the scenario? אילימא נתן צרור
וסכר מיא מינה, eillima natan tzeror ve-sachar maya mineh,
that you put in a rock in a wall that had an
opening, there was a hole in the wall, and you prevented water
from entering into the field. Okay there was some flood or something,
the river overflowed, whatever it was, it was torrential rains, and water
was going to go into the field because there was this hole
in the wall and you sealed the hole in the wall. So
that's a pretty significant contribution. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's
the story there? So the גמרא Gemara says, where was it? מאי
נתן ומאי נטל? mai natan u-mai natal? אילימא נתן צרור וסכר מיא
מינה, eillima natan tzeror ve-sachar maya mineh, נטל צרור ואפיק מיא מינה.
natal tzeror ve-afik maya mineh.
Or let's say the field was flooding and the water couldn't escape
and it needed to escape so it wouldn't wash, wouldn't destroy the
field and you removed a rock and you let the water go
out of the field, it was the opposite direction the water was
going and that was necessary otherwise the field would have, would have
like the ground would have become submerged. So in that case the
גמרא Gemara says האי מבריח ארי מנכסי חברו הוא. hai mavriach ari
mi-nichsei chaveiro hu.
That's not חזקה. chazakah. You're just chasing a lion away from your
friend's field because you're just preventing damage. Now what does that mean
that you're preventing? So it sounds like that you know because that
act, there's a couple ways of framing this. One way of framing
this is like any normal person who sees their friend's property that's
about to be damaged should try to do something to protect it.
So the way this act is going to be interpreted is you're
just trying to like protect the land. You're not trying you know
because of some imminent damage that's about to occur. So that's not
an act of like of ownership, that's just an act of being
a good you know neighbor. You know that's just you know that's
just an act of protecting somebody's property. So that might require that
the potential damage be imminent. And the reason I raise this is
because there's an interesting debate of the רשבם Rashbam and תוספות, Tosafot,
I mentioned this yesterday, of the case of locking the gate where
the רשבם Rashbam says if you just lock the gate it's not
enough of, it's not a חזקה. chazakah. Why not? If you install
a lock, it is. But if you just close the gate, it
isn't. Why not? So one thing you could say is because you
didn't create any structural change to it. You didn't sort of you
know you didn't do any type of an improvement. But the but
the reason but yes but the reason the רשבם Rashbam says it's
no good is because he says you're מבריח ארי מנכסי חברו. mavriach
ari mi-nichsei chaveiro. Because by closing, if I walk by and I
see your door open like you know and I close your door
for you because I don't want people to walk into your house
and walk into your field, I'm just doing like a good neighborly
thing here. I'm preventing you know people from possible damage. So therefore
that wouldn't work because that is interpreted as protecting it from some
damage that might immediately occur. You know that might or in the
near future occur. And not as an actual improvement of the field.
Now תוספות Tosafot disagree. תוספות Tosafot say that would not be a
problem. Why not? I mean that actually would be good just closing
the door. Why would it not be מבריח ארי? mavriach ari? So
the one thing that I could think to say is because the
most obvious thing is because the damage isn't imminent. Right? When the
damage is imminent and I'm stopping the damage, then my act is
totally looked as blocking, preventing damage. Right? It's not looked as some
more sense of showing, demonstrating my ownership of the field, improving the
field. It's more looked as preventing this imminent thing. Whereas if I
close the door, it's not imminent. Right? The possible fact that somebody
might come in. But if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot
he gives a slightly different reason. תוספות Tosafot says the following. He
says,
it's about the previous עמוד? amud? Yeah it starts there, but I'm
going to go in the middle. He says like this. He
says it's about one, two, three, four, five lines down. Putting a
lock in, no? That's the קשיא. kashya. So whether or not means
putting in a lock, which is what the רשבם Rashbam says because
he says to just lock it would be מבריח ארי. mavriach ari.
Okay. But תוספות Tosafot disagree. תוספות Tosafot says just locking it could
be that it is a חזקה. chazakah. And if you go ten
lines down on נג עמוד א nun gimmel amud aleph the תוספות
Tosafot began from the previous עמוד amud but ten lines down in
the narrow lines the line starts with the word לקמן, lekaman, תוספות
Tosafot says the
following: ולא דמי נעילת דלת למבריח ארי. ve-lo dami ne'ilat delet le-mavriach
ari. Locking the door is not like מבריח ארי. mavriach ari. So
again I would have said because the damage isn't imminent. But here's
what תוספות Tosafot says. למבריח ארי le-mavriach ari אבל הכא שנועל בפני
כל אדם, aval hacha she-no'el bifnei kol adam, but here that he
locks in front of every person ואין
מניח אדם ליכנס ve-ein mani'ach adam leikanes and doesn't let a person
enter, in that case so he says מוכח מילתא שהבית הוא שלו
וקני בנעילה לחוד. muchach milta she-habayit hu shelo ve-kani be-ne'ila le-chud.
So he says less that it's not מבריח ארי mavriach ari like
oh you're not just preventing damage because it's not imminent. More the
question is like the positive definition. Not like מבריח ארי mavriach ari
is a problem. But as long as your act shows that you're
acting like the owner, then that is considered a חזקה. chazaka. So
what an owner does is the normal responsible ownership is you lock
your house before you leave. You lock your door, your car door
after you leave, right? That's what owners do, is that they protect
their property when they're leaving. So even though it sounds like תוספות
Tosafos in the גמרא, Gemara, it might be an element of מבריח
ארי, mavriach ari, you're protecting it from damage. The more important point
is that it's a normal type of an
act that demonstrates ownership. Okay, so in the end of the day
what we're saying is that certain types of things might create an
immediate improve, do something that benefits, but it's not seen as the
act of an owner. It's seen as just like preventing damage, whereas
when it is, there could be times you are preventing damage but
in a context, which is what תוספות Tosafos says, that preventing possible
future damage is the way not that an immediate bypasser who's trying
to help you out acts, but the way that an owner acts.
Yes. Okay, I was confused in the between parts. Doesn't the beginning
of the תוספות Tosafos say just the opposite? He quotes the רשבם.
Rashbam. The גמרא Gemara פירש peireish רשבם. Rashbam. He quotes the רשבם
Rashbam and then he challenges it. Ah, right. So the same act,
in one case is you're helping your neighbor and the other when
you're actually taking away from him. Well, you're not taking away, you're
not doing this adversely. The person is trying to transfer the property
to you, right? Yes. So the question is, but the purpose of
חזקה chazaka is to act in a way that an owner acts.
And it seems like the idea of מבריח ארי mavriach ari is
of course an owner would protect their property, but anybody would try
to protect the property of somebody that they see that's about to
be damaged. Okay, but if it's, but תוספות Tosafos deals with that.
Okay, but there are ways in which you can protect the property
that looks more like the way an owner acts and not the
way some bypasser would act to come to take protection. This is
very functional just in places that people don't lock. The people don't
lock. Right, exactly.
Yes, it's very like a בני ברקיש Bnei Brakish culture. Right, exactly,
exactly. He also has interesting questions, does נעל na'al always mean lock
or can it sometimes mean really just to close the door, so,
but yes. Okay, so that's that. Now the other thing that's relevant
here also is that might be part of what the מבריח ארי
mavriach ari is, is not just that it's about preventing damage, which
is like something that anybody would try to do to help you
out, but also an issue we're going to get to, which is
how much have you actually changed the field, done something to the
field. So if you build a wall, you change the structure. If
you open an opening, you change the structure. So you could say
well, I prevented the field from being damaged. Oh, but preventing it
from being damaged is not the same as improving it, right? So
maybe part of the problem here is not so much that it's
the way an owner—a bypasser could act and not an owner could
act, but it's more of a technical point, that חזקה chazaka is
only when the field is improved in the process. And you didn't
improve it. You prevented it from being damaged but you didn't improve
it, right? So to prevent my car from being scratched is not
the same as giving my car a wax job, or
giving some touch up paint. So you might have to actually improve
the field and not just prevent damage. And that's another way of
understanding what מבריח ארי mavriach ari is. So now let's see what
the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ella,
here's the case where it works, נתן צרור וצמדה למיא. nasan tzror
vitzamid la lemaya.
You put in a rock which actually kept the water in. It's
the reverse. If there's been rain in the field, and you actually
don't want the water to go out. You want the rain to
stay in the field so that it continues to water the field.
So and and it's going to be coming out through an opening
in the wall, so you close the wall to keep the rain
in. Okay, so that's a case of caring for the field. It's
not preventing a damage. It's not מבריח ארי. mavriach ari. And also,
it's improving the field. It's irrigating the field. So that's an improvement,
that's not a prevention of damage. Okay,
that's one case. Or נטל צרור וארחה למיא. natol tzror ve'arvach la
lemaya. Or you took out a rock and that actually allowed water
to get in. You weren't trying to get, it's the opposite. You're
trying to get water in the field. So there's some water passing
by and you're saying oh, I could use my field to be
watered or you take out the rock and it lets the water
go in and water the field. So rather than preventing the field
from being flooded, we're having the cases of נטל צרור natol tzror
and נתן צרור natan tzror as to keep water in the field.
And that is a type of a thing which is not about
preventing damage, it's about caring for the field. It's about actually improving
the field, not just stopping it from being hurt. Okay, and that's
what a חזקה chazaka is, about the improving of the field. Okay,
so isn't it the same thing as the—but water was either coming
in or going out.
The same act can either be preventing damage, yeah, depending on exactly
the
circumstances, right, and what you want, exactly. ואמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן שתי שדות V'amar Rav Asi Amar Rabbi Yochanan shtei sadot ומצר
אחד ביניהם. u'metzar echad beineihem.
Now
this is a slightly different issue. This is not going to be
the what constitutes the act of חזקה, chazakah, but like the plot
of land upon it which it works.
You have two adjoining fields and you've got a boundary marker between
them. You know, it could just be a slightly raised piece of
dirt that runs along the boundary, you know, maybe there's some white
plaster, there's some boundary marker between them. והחזיק באחת מהן לקנותה, v'hechezik
b'achat mehen liknotah,
and you did a חזקה chazakah on one of them to buy
it. קנה, knah, then you bought the one that you did the
חזקה chazakah on. Again, this is if it's being sold or a
הפקר. hefker. Okay, לקנות אותה ואת חברתה, liknot otah v'et chavertah,
now let's say you're trying to acquire both of them, let's say
they're both הפקר, hefker, they're both like a case of a גר
ger that died. אותה קנה וחברתה לא קנה. otah kanah v'chavertah lo
kanah. It only works for that field, not for the neighboring one.
Since the fields are demarcated as separate, a חזקה chazakah on one
field does not work on the other. לקנות את חברתה, liknot et
chavertah, and similarly, if you were doing it on field A but
trying to use your חזקה chazakah to work on field B, אף
אותה לא קנה. af otah lo kanah. You didn't even you weren't
even קונה koneh field A because you know you did not even
though you could say well I did a חזקה chazakah on A,
but it was an unintentional חזקה, chazakah, you know, which is an
interesting question. Let's say there's a הפקר, hefker, I don't know, let's
say somebody drops a הפקר hefker iPhone, I'm always with my iPhone,
into my Starbucks bag over there and I'm completely unaware, and then
I pick up my Starbucks bag to go you know to go
somewhere and I put it down in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash
and then somebody says oh look a הפקר hefker iPhone and they
grab it out of my bag. Can I say oh I was
already—what, was there an iPhone there? No, I was already קונה koneh
בהגבהה? b'hagbahah? No, you can't say that because if even though you
did a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan on an object that was הפקר,
hefker, it's not considered a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan if you weren't
intending it to act as such. Okay, so therefore when I'm doing
חזקה chazakah in field A and I'm only intending it to work
for field B, even though you could say I'm intending to do
a מעשה חזקה, ma'aseh chazakah, but since I'm not intending to do
an act of חזקה chazakah on field A, it doesn't work on
field A. So with this boundary line, the חזקה chazakah can only
work on field A. If you tried to do A and B,
you get A. If you try to do A, you get A.
If you try to do B, you don't even get A because
even though you did the right act, you weren't intending it to
work for field A, which is the only field it can work
for. Okay, so that's this הלכה halachah that it only works on
that particular field. Now there's an important discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim,
which is one minute, the גמרא Gemara in קידושין, Kiddushin, which is
the major source of discussing קניינים, kinyanim, says if I'm trying to
sell Gloria here two of my fields, one is here and one
is in Florida, and I say to Gloria, Gloria, do a חזקה
chazakah on this field and you'll own this one and the one
in Florida. Completely separate, right? The הלכה halachah is it works. It
does work. Because basically we consider like all land is connected. Okay,
I don't know what happens when you try to do it across
continents, but we won't worry about that right now, okay? So that
actually works. So everybody says so I don't understand, here they're right
next to each other, there's just a little boundary marker, why should
it not work? So there's two basic answers and there is a
practical difference. One answer is that the גמרא Gemara is that maybe
the only case it works when I'm trying to sell Gloria my
plot in New York and plot in Florida is if she paid
me for both of them. She's already paid me. And it's a
case where as we said, you know, sometimes כסף kesef under certain
contexts doesn't work by itself. So since she's paid me for both
of them, that automatically and I have an obligation to you know
to give her for you know the field for the money she
gave me, that automatically like brings both fields into the equation. And
therefore she's doing it on one, it works for both, because both
have been paid for. Okay, as opposed to this case, let's say
this case would be הפקר. hefker. It would be a case of
a גר ger who died. So since there's no money that brings
them together, they're treated individually. That's one distinction. The other distinction is
that—and maybe even if she didn't pay me, maybe just the fact
that she's obligating herself to pay me, but the fact that she
says I will be קונה koneh this and owe you you know
20,000 dollars, 10,000 for each field, maybe that's what brings them together.
Okay, the other possible difference is between הפקר hefker and this case
is the principle something in הלכה halachah called דעת אחרת מקנה אותו.
da'at acheret maknah oto.
Another דעת, da'at, like mind, you know, intention is trying to to
affect the transfer. So it's so even though Gloria's act is only
on the one field, I the seller am intending to give her
both fields and my intention to transfer both combines them and lets
the one act work for both. As opposed to if it's הפקר,
hefker, you don't have the other side. It's just you operating unilaterally.
So if you're operating unilaterally, what is combining—you need more the objective
reality to be one thing. There's no external force that's combining them.
No money and no intention, just the external reality, and if they're
demarcated, they're not one field. So the important נפקא מינה nafka mina
between these two approaches is a מתנה. matanah. gift. Let's say I'm
trying to gift Gloria my two fields. So you have the דעת
אחרת מקנה, daas acheres makneh, but you don't have the money. So
would that be enough to combine those two and say a חזקה
chazakah on one works on the other? Okay, so that's an interesting
discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim that there are definitely times when you
do a חזקה chazakah on one field it works on another, but
in at least a case of הפקר, hefker, everybody agrees, whatever the
story is by מתנה, matanah, at least in the case of הפקר
hefker where there's no money and nobody else that's whose דעת daas
is pulling those fields together, then the חזקה chazakah only works on
the field that it is done. And even if it's a continuous
plot of land, the line of demarcation is enough to define them
as two separate plots. Yes, Jenna? So the last bit where you
do the חזקה chazakah on field B instead of field A? Yeah.
You did the חזקה chazakah on field A but you wanted it
to work for field B. Right. Right. Wait, I don't understand, how
would that happen? I went ahead and I build a fence on
field A, they're all connected.
Right. For field A and B? What? You want in that case
you want it to work for field A and B? Right. No,
there's two... all these pens have dried out. Okay. You did it
on the wrong... Here, yes.
Here's the line of demarcation, right? Here's field A and here's field
B. You went ahead and you built up a little fence over
here, okay, or you opened an opening over here. Now you were
saying like, and I want it to work for that field. So
you're just saying what type of idiot does that? Okay, I don't
know the answer. Okay? Maybe the point was it was like, you
know, you widened an opening, so you said, 'Oh look, here's an
opening, this will be easy for me to widen, I just have
to like, you know, cut away a little bit more, this is
an easy place for me to do my חזקה, chazakah, okay, and
it's all connected,
so it should work for everything, I'm not really interested in this,
but it's all connected so let it work.' That was basically what
you were, you know, but you're right, it's a bizarre
case. Okay, it's
a bizarre scenario. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בעי רבי זירא, Bayei Rabbi Zeira, so Rabbi Zeira asked, החזיק באחת
מהן לקנות אותה ואת המיצר ואת חברתה מהו? Hechzik be'achas mehen liknos
osah v'es hametzar v'es chavertah mahu?
Let's say, right, you basically did a חזקה chazakah here, and with
your act of חזקה, chazakah, you basically said, 'I want it not
just to work...' when you want it to work for A and
B, you only get A, not B. But let's say, and presumably
here we have to assume the way the רשב"ם Rashbam is saying,
that this מיצר metzar is like, I don't know, like a little
mound of earth, okay, some little, you know, three טפח tefach little
mound of earth that divides the two fields. And you're doing this
חזקה chazakah and you're saying, 'You know what? I want this to
work not for A and B, then it'll only work for A,
I want it to work for A and the mound of earth
and B.' So maybe because I want to include the mound of
earth, I'm able to look at it as all just one... I'm
not going to look at this as a dividing line. I'm going
to look at this as one big field with a little mound
of earth in the middle. So I'll get the mound of earth
together, let me look at it as all one field. Okay, what's
the
story, מהו? mahu? So ואת המיצר ואת חברתה מהו? v'es hametzar v'es
chavertah mahu? מי אמרינן מיצר דארעא חד הוא? Mi amrinan metzar de'ara
chad hu? The mound with the land is all one thing. There's
a slightly different גרסא girsa which is maybe a little clearer: האי
מיצר דהאי ארעא ודהאי ארעא הוא. Hai metzar dehai ara u'dehai ara
hu. This mound, this line, is connected to this field and to
that field. So basically the point is, if I want to do
it together with that mound, it's all one big field, let me
look at it as all one big field, okay, וקני u'kani and
it works, או דלמא לא האי לחוד קאי והאי לחוד קאי? o
dilma lo hai lechud ka'i v'hai lechud ka'i? No, you can't do
it, they're the two separate fields and the מיצר, metzar, the boundary
line, is a separate unit, and at the end of the day,
even with your intent to do it all together, they remain separate
units. So the גמרא Gemara says, what does the גמרא Gemara say?
תיקו. Teiku. Okay, we don't know. בעי רב אלעזר. Bayei Rav Elazar.
Now Rav Elazar asked. החזיק במיצר לקנות שתיהן מהו? Hechzik bametzar liknos
shteihen mahu? How about if I did a חזקה chazakah on this
little mound of earth? Okay, I don't know, I you know, I
dug in it and I planted some stuff, I watered it, whatever
I did, okay, I added to it, I did some חזקה. chazakah.
So maybe to try to get some here, which because of the
מיצר metzar is defined as a separate unit, I can't transcend that
and say I'm going to incorporate the divider and look at it
as all one thing. But maybe if I start at the divider,
right, where both of these fields in a way are connected to
the divider because it divides, it serves both fields to divide them
from the other.
Well that’s true too. Because you see you were not קונה koneh
either A or B. You were קונה... koneh... Yeah, but if you’re
trying to be קונה koneh the
mound it would be a hard argument that you wouldn’t get the
things that you actually doing the חזקה chazakah to. You’re קונה koneh
a boundary. No, no, but the boundary is an actual physical raised
mound of earth. That’s the way the רשב"ם Rashbam is explaining it.
Fine, a second ago we conceived of it as simply part of
A or simply part of B. All right, so that’s what part
of the question is. And if you grow something on that mound
it’s his mound. Right, well that’s always a question. Who owns the
no-man’s land? Who owns the boundary? Okay, so...
okay, so... בעא ר' אלעזר: Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar: החזיק במיצר לקנות שתיהן
מהו? Hizik bemeitzar liknot shteihen ma hu? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do
we say האי מיצר אפסרא דארעא הוא, Hai meitzar afsara de-ara hu,
it is like the bridle? I think that’s what an אפסרא afsara
is. An אפסרא afsara bridle... the reins. Okay, thanks. What’s the difference?
The bridle is where it goes around the mouth and the reins
are the... okay. You usually say the bit, right? For the reins
have to... the bridle. So anyway, so it’s like... like... if I...
so if I do... if I’m trying to buy a horse and
I do a קנין kinyan on the reins while they’re attached to
the horse, it’s like קנין kinyan on the horse because it sort
of like controls the horse. It’s funny, it’s like secondary to the
horse. You might have said the opposite: do a קנין kinyan on
the horse and you get the reins, you schlep along the stuff
that’s secondary. But since it’s also there to serve to like protect
and control and so on, it actually is sort of seen as
representing the ownership over it, taking the reins and so on. So
therefore this is serving to protect these lands. These are like the
reins on the land and they show protection and control. So therefore,
and since it has that symbolic significance for both A and B,
or that functional significance for A and B, doing the קנין kinyan
on it allows me to be קונה koneh both A and B.
Do we say that? Okay...
וקני, ve-kani, it works. או דלמא האי לחודיה קאי והאי לחודיה קאי?
O delma hai lechuda kai vehai lechuda kai? No, I’m sorry buddy.
At the end of the day, the purpose of this is to
divide the two plots of land. So therefore you cannot bring those
plots together. Okay, and the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says, is not
only are A and B separate, but the mound is also separate.
Right? The mound is not a part of A or part of
B. There are three separate units here: A, the boundary, and B.
And none of them are connected to any one. Each is maintained
as a separate unit.
But if he plows through from A through the divider to B,
then that would work, sure, because then he did a חזקה chazakah
on B. Right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this...
okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוּה: Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabba bar Avuha: שני בתים זה לפנים מזה. Shtei batim zeh lifnim
mizeh.
So now, here’s a slightly different case than the two fields because
you have a case where you’ve got a house, here’s the רשות
הרבים... reshut harabbim...
okay, here’s the door to the house... all right, and you have
the outer house and the inner house. And the only way the
guy on the inside, there’s no back door, the only way the
guy on the inside gets to his house and he goes outside
is through the outer house. Okay? And now again, this whole house
becomes הפקר. hefker. So what’s going to be the story?
Let’s take a look. שני בתים זה לפנים מזה. Shtei batim zeh
lifnim mizeh. החזיק בחיצון... Hechezik bachitzon...
by the way, I do find this interesting, I just want to
pause for a second, like the idea of the מיצר, meitzar, that
we are conceptualizing this as two units. Meaning, let’s say you had
a גר ger that owned an apartment building. Okay, he owned like
a
brownstone... and there were three flights, three stories to it. Sometimes people...
like maybe if there was a time where he rented out the
top stories or whatever, but now the whole thing is vacant, okay?
And he dies. And you go ahead and you do a חזקה
chazakah on the ground level. Are you saying you don’t have a
חזקה chazakah on the rest? They’re all one structure, right? So on
the one hand they’re divided, they’re on separate floors, you got to
go out... you have to use external stairs to get up to
the separate units, right? But at the end of the day, there’s
a reality that they’re one structure. So there’s a חידוש chidush that
we’re going to look at that as that those are separate houses
and you would have to do a חזקה chazakah on each one.
As opposed to the fields, right? The fields there’s no structure that
unifies them. It’s just all consistent land. So first of all there’s
a חידוש chidush here that we’re going to view this as like
the two fields, as two houses and not say at the end
of the day even if you,
for all you wanted, I could have my kids live in the
back and I could live in the front. Right? So what is
it that clearly makes everything inside one structure into two separate units?
I understand there’s a wall here, there’s a door, I tend to
rent this out. But again, I think that’s a... we should just
recognize that there’s like an assumption here.
Well,
the point is now it's all הפקר. hefker. That's why we can
have a discussion if doing it on one part works on the
other, right? But like let's say a car is הפקר, hefker, there's
still a like there's still a registration on the car, right? Oh,
I see. Would let's say the apartment building filed with the city
as three separate residences or was it filed as one building? That's
interesting. Yeah, הלכה halacha does not have the same, does not have
these central registry type of things. But that's what? Yeah, I would
think one building because if I have a friend who owns a
building, right? It's just like a, it's defined as three-story, three separate
apartments. He rents them out, right? But he owns the building. Right.
Right. So if he dies and I want to go ahead and
take possession of it. Now, it might be more complicated if other
people are in the other sections, but like everybody, you know, it's
between, between, you know, tenants, right? Would I have to do three
separate חזקה? chazakah? So that's what I'm asking. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says here. Okay. And you could throw those people
out? I understand. You could throw them out. Yeah, I understand. But
you, but if they're still living there, they might by default automatically
like be in חזקה. chazakah. Anyway, whatever. Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, שני בתים
זה לפנים מזה. shnei batim zeh lifnim mizeh. החזיק בחיצון לקנותו, Hechzik
bechitzon liknoto, קנאו. knao. If you,
so
same point. You want to do this, it works. לקנותו ואת הפנימי,
Liknoto ve'et hapnimi,
you try to, you have this gain work for, for both A
and B. So החיצון קנה פנימי לא קנה. hachitzon kanah pnimi lo
kanah.
It only works for the outer. לקנות את הפנימי, Liknot et hapnimi,
if you only want it to work for the inner, but you're
doing the חזקה chazakah on the outer, אף החיצון לא קנה. af
hachitzon lo kanah. It doesn't work at all. So that's just like
the field. Now we get to what happens if you do the
inner side. החזיק בפנימי לקנותו, Hechzik bipnimi liknoto,
if you do the inner one just to get, just to get
it, it works. Just to get B. קנאו. knao. לקנותו ואת החיצון,
Liknoto ve'et hachitzon, if you did B to get B and A,
קנה שניהם. kanah shneihem.
Here it's different. Here it does work for both. Okay, and I'll
get back to that in a minute. לקנות את החיצון אף הפנימי
לא קנה. Liknot et hachitzon af hapnimi lo kanah. But if it's
just to get A, it doesn't work. Now, before, first I want
to pause and say that the רי''ף Rif and the רמב''ם Rambam
and other ראשונים Rishonim have a גרסה girsa that says this is,
that is different than our גמרא, Gemara, that says this is exactly
like the case of the field. That it doesn't matter inner or
outer, it only can work for itself and it can't work for
the other one. Our version of the גמרא Gemara is more interesting
because it's different than the field. And it says that if you
do it for the inner, it works for the outer. And presumably,
the reason is is that since use of the inner requires passage
through the outer,
requires use of the outer, so therefore, the outer is seen as
somewhat connected to the inner, right? The inner isn't connected to the
outer because the outer exists by itself. But somehow because the inner
is dependent on the outer, needs to use the outer, that could
be seen as an extension of the inner and therefore can be,
you know, it can all work together. So you could fence two
adjacent fields like this inner and outer where you could only have
access to one of the fields through... Yeah, I assume if you
were to replicate that type of a thing by a field, then
it might be that it could work. It's not intrinsic to land,
it's intrinsic to the way in which it's functioning. Correct. Okay.
Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha, הבונה פלטירין, haboneh palterin, now this is the biggest
חידוש, chiddush, הבונה פלטירין גדולים בנכסי הגר. haboneh palterin gedolim benichsei hager.
So we're dealing again with the נכסי הגר, nichsei hager, a גר
ger died, he's got his field that's הפקר. hefker. And let's even
not make it a field because it'll make it more interesting. It's
basically he's got a yard, he has a, you know, in in
the middle of the town, okay? He's got a vacant lot. And
I come along, and rather than building a fence on the lot
or opening up, opening in the fence on the lot, what I
do is I build a house on the lot. Okay? Now, all
of us would think that's pretty darn good
חזקה. chazakah. You've definitely now radically improved the value of the field,
okay? So it says, so it says ובא אחר והעמיד להן דלתות.
uva acher vehe'emid lahen dlatot. But you built the whole house, but
you didn't put the doors in the house yet. And somebody else
comes and he puts in the doors, קנה. kanah. The other guy
is קונה koneh everything. Now, you of course can get reimbursed for
your house, okay? But he's קונה koneh the field and he owns
it all. Now, he might not, again, own, it's an interesting question,
right? If you're building a house on somebody's property, right? Like like
that's like let's say, סתם, stam, I just go to your property
and I build a house. Who has, I'm entitled to be reimbursed,
but who has title to the house, right? So could be it's
in your property you wind up having, is it my title and
you have to buy it off of me or whatever? This assumes
that I built this house and whatever. I might be able to
get reimbursed for my labor, but at the end of the day,
because it's a house on somebody else's property, he's going to assume
title of the house and the property, okay? And
you know, he goes by because of what? Because he's the one
that did the חזקה chazakah on the plot of land. Now, why
is it, one minute, why is it that building a whole house
is not a חזקה chazakah on a plot of land and putting
doors in the house is? One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why is that? קמא, kama, the first
guy, לבני בעלמא הוא דאפיך. livnei be'alma hu de'apich. Yeah,
he just put some bricks down. He didn't really do anything. Now,
that's not exactly so helpful, okay? What do you mean he just
put some bricks down? He radically improved the value of the land.
So let's look So let's look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says,
לבני באלמא הוא דאפיך, livni b'alma hu de'apich, he just turned over
some bricks. ואף אגב דרפיק בה פורתא, ve'af agav derafik bah purta,
so תוספות Tosafot
has a couple questions. First of all, a classic חזקה chazakah is
like, you know, turning over the ground, digging in the ground. So
if you're building a house, you're digging a whole foundation. So he
says, כשבנה יסוד, keshebana yesod, when he built the foundation, לא מהני
מידי, lo mahani midi, that doesn't help at all, אלא בקרקע העומד
לחרישה, ella bekarka haomed lacharrisha,
when does digging work? If you're going to be plowing and planting.
ולא דמי, velo dami, now one minute, but so what? So you're
improving it by creating a house. So he says, ולא דמי למוצא
פלטרין בנויין וסד בהן סיוד אחד דקנה. velo dami lemotzei paltarin benuyin
vesad bahen siyud echad dekani.
We're about to get a case where in the גמרא Gemara that
I come and a גר ger died and there's this gorgeous, you
know, mansion he has, and I come and I plaster the door,
or I come and I make a little, you know, engraving on
the wall or something. That's a קנין. kinyan. That's a חזקה. chazakah.
So how could making a plaster on the wall or an engraving
be a חזקה chazakah and building a house not be a חזקה?
chazakah? So let's see what תוספות Tosafot says.
וסד בהן סיוד אחד דקנה דהתם משביח בנכסי הגר דהיינו פלטרין vesad
bahen siyud echad dekani dehatam mashpiach benichsei hager deinu paltarin because there,
what is the property? The property is the house. The house is
what I'm trying to do a קנין kinyan on in the case
where he died and left a house behind. And I improve the
house by doing a little plastering or a little engraving. Okay, אבל
הכא מאי נכסי הגר aval hacha mai nichsei hager here, what is
the property I'm trying to be קונה? koneh? Not the house. The
house doesn't exist. I'm trying to be קונה koneh the plot of
land. הוא קרקע. hu karka. והיא לא נשתבחה. vehi lo nishtabcha. Now
what do you mean the קרקע karka isn't improved? I just put
a house on the land. So he says, שאין ראויה לדור שם
כל זמן שאין דלתות. she'ein rauyah ledur sham kol zeman she'ein dlatot.
Okay, so he says, because building a house does not yet improve
it functionally. It definitely improved it property value. But it hasn't improved
it functionally until the house is ready to be lived in. Okay,
like for example, they did this whole new building on the שול,
shul, right? They had the whole שול shul built and they needed
to get what's those called? A temporary certificate of occupancy. A certificate
of occupancy. Until you get a certificate of occupancy, you're not allowed
to dwell in it. So nobody lives in a house that doesn't
have doors. Okay, so since even though now the property is worth
a million dollars more, okay, functionally it hasn't been improved yet because
there's no new function you can do on the property. So wait
a minute, if you've got a house and you went ahead and
you improved it, you did a little engraving or plastering, you've made
it a nicer house and you've made it a better house. But
I have not made this yet functionally a better field if it's
not ready to be lived in the house. תוספות Tosafot says one
minute, maybe you can't live in the house but you can go
and get shelter, let's say it's in the middle of a rain.
So that's the next line of תוספות. Tosafot. He says, ואם תאמר
והיש בה גג וראוי להכנס בה מחמה מפני החמה ומגשם מפני הגשמים,
ve'im tomar vahayeish bah gag verauy lehikanes bah mechamma mipnei hachamma u'migsham
mipnei hageshamim,
you can take shelter in it. יש לומר דבכל מקום לא חזי
לדירת קבע כל זמן שאין בה דלתות. yeish lomar debichol makom lo
chazi ledira keva kol zeman she'ein bah dlatot. As long as there
are no doors, you're not going to live in it permanently, which
doesn't really answer the question, you can still get some temporary benefit.
But that's maybe not seen as a benefit of the land. The
land has to be something ongoing. אדרבה קילקל דמעיקרא חזי לזריעה והשתא
לא חזי לזריעה. adarabba kilkel deme'ikara chazi lizeria vehashta lo chazi lizeria.
Before you built this lousy mansion, I could have had some tomatoes
here. You ruined my tomato plot! Okay, so anyway, so down of
the farm land. Right. I know. So, yeah, I don't know, it's
a good point. He started by saying it's not ראוי rauy lachavira,
I don't know what to say. But he basically point is that
you have made the plot unusable,
you've prevented other uses, and the use that you were trying to
create is not yet operative. Okay, so therefore you have not yet
improved the land in a practical way yet. Okay, so first of
all, this is a fantastic תוספות. Tosafot. Yes,
you see it all the time in this neighborhood. You see often
in Spuyten Duyvil a house and all the windows are boarded up.
That's because they're doing renovations in it. It's legally it's not habitable
without windows or boards. You don't have to pay taxes, you don't
have to pay real estate taxes if it's not habitable. That's a
good point. Old houses there, there are several houses in Spuyten Duyvil
like that, beautiful homes, but they're doing work and it's taking a
long time so they make it uninhabitable. Right, right, uninhabitable, yeah. All
right, very good. All right, so let's take a look then. The
גמרא Gemara says... okay, so that's got to be the most radical
statement of this דף. daf.
Okay. אמר רב דימי בר יוסף אמר רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Dimi
bar Yosef amar Rebbi Elazar, המוצא פלטרין בנכסי הגר, hamotzei paltarin benichsei
hager, so now it's the case that תוספות Tosafot already referred to.
Let's say you're not the issue, the focus is not on the
land, you actually start with a mansion there,
בנכסי הגר, benichsei hager, now I lost my place, וסד בהן סיוד
אחד, vesad bahen siyud echad, and you did a little plastering.
Or a little engraving, קנאן, kna'an, you're קונה koneh because now you've
improved the house. וכמה? vekama? How much? אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, אמה. amah. It has to be an אמה amah long, otherwise
it's completely trivial. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, וכנגד הפתח, uchneged
hapetach, and that's also if you're doing a plastering, it's also in
a place that it's visible. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says if I
understand the רשב"ם Rashbam correctly means you open the door if you're
doing an indoor plastering you see it as soon as you open
the door, it's like on the facing wall. But if it's not
as immediately visible then you might have to do a more a
bigger job. It has to be some type of a substantive thing.
So if it's immediately visible, oh look at this nice plaster job
you got, oh look at this nice engraving, then that's but if
it's more hidden then it would not be enough. There has to
be a minimum sense of like some type of an improvement, you
know. What? To go go around looking for נכסי הגר. nichsei hager.
Right. You have to go find them. Good job. Right. Right.
You know there's that funny little scene from the movie that tried
to find an apartment in Manhattan and the guy who like was
reading the obituaries you know to find out like which apartments might
be available. He said you know they should cross-reference the obituaries with
the
you know. John Smith died leaves behind you know a wife and
two children and a lovely three-bedroom walk-up.
Anyway.
What? Yeah exactly. Anyway so there is like this all right. אמר
רב עמרם, Amar Rav Amram, said רב עמרם, Rav Amram, האי
מילתא אמר לן רב ששת, Hai milta amar lan Rav Sheshet, the
following thing רב ששת Rav Sheshet said to us and he said
it like on his own, you know, his own idea, ואנהרן עינין,
ve'anharnu einin, and he lit up our eyes, I love that phrase,
ממתניתא, mimatnita, and in the end he showed us that you know
this actually this idea he had on his own he was really
could be found implicit in a ברייתא. braitah. What's this idea? He
said the following: המציע מצעות בנכסי הגר. Hamatzia matza'ot benichsei hager. Now
we're getting back to the concrete act of קנין. kinyan. You go
ahead and they left the land and you what you're going to
do is you're going to do a camp out. Okay? You're going
to take your mattress and you're going to put it on the
land and you're going to sleep on the land tonight. Is that
going to be a קנין? kinyan? Now from everything we've learned the
answer should be no because you haven't improved the land. Okay? קנאה.
kana.
What? המציע hamatzia is to spread?
No, it's a mat, a spread out, a spread, a mattress. But
the presumption is you spread it out and you slept there. You
didn't just spread it out. Now some ראשונים rishonim say by the
way that if you just slept straight on the ground without the
mattress it wouldn't work because that's not דרך derech like you know
it's very hard it's not comfortable but in a way that would
be a normal way that people would you know could enjoy the
land by putting a mattress on it doing a little camp out
and sleeping on it that would work. So you spread out these
mattresses and you slept there. קנאה. kana. It works. Which is surprising
based on what we've been saying.
ואנהרן עינין ממתניתא. ve'anharnu einin mimatnita. And he lit up our eyes
from the ברייתא. braitah. Why? דתניא, detanya, we learned in a ברייתא,
braitah, כיצד בחזקה, keitzad bechazakah, this is going back a ברייתא braitah
from קידושין Kiddushin about that land is acquired with חזקה chazakah but
also slaves are acquired with חזקה. chazakah. Slaves and lands are the
same. כסף שטר וחזקה. kesef shtar vechazakah. What's the חזקה chazakah of
a slave?
נעלו מנעלו, na'alo min'alo, if you get the the slave to tie
your shoe for you, או התיר לו מנעלו, o hitir lo min'alo,
or to untie your shoe, או שהוליך כליו אחריו לבית המרחץ, o
sheholich kelav acharay l'veit hamerchatz, he brings you know your clothes and
your whatever your bathing equipment to you to the bathhouse, הפשיטו, hifshito,
or he undresses you in the bathhouse, והרחצו, vehirtzo, he bathes you,
סכו, sacho, he rubs the oil onto your body, גרדו, gardo, he
like scrapes you, והלבישו, vehilbisho,
he dresses you, והנעילו, vehin'ilo, puts on your shoe although we mentioned
that before, והגביהו, vehigbiho, or he lifts you up, let's say you
know you're trying to get out of some place and he helps
pick you up, okay? קנאו, kna'o, that works. So and now אמר
רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, לא תהא חזקה גדולה מהגבהה, lo tehei
chazakah gedolah mehagbahah, you know what? This חזקה chazakah should not be
any better than הגבהה, hagbahah, שהגבהה קונה בכל מקום, shehagbahah konah bechol
makom, הגבהה hagbahah always works. So huh? So גמרא Gemara says, מאי
קאמר, mai ka'amar, what I don't understand. First of all let's figure
out this ברייתא. braitah. What is
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying? Who's picking up whom is exactly it.
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's what he's implicitly saying: הגביהו לרבו קנאו.
higbiho l'rabbo kna'o. If I use the slave like all the earlier
examples, he serviced me, he picked me up, then that works. He
did a service to me. הגביה רבו לו, higbia rabbo lo, but
implicit in the תנא קמא tanna kamma is, if I were to
pick up the slave, לא קנאו, lo kna'o, that wouldn't be קנין
הגבהה kinyan hagbahah by a slave, there's a קנין חזקה. kinyan chazakah.
And אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
disagrees and he says לא תהא חזקה גדולה מהגבהה שהגבהה קונה בכל
מקום. lo tehei chazakah gedolah mehagbahah shehagbahah konah bechol makom. No, I'm
sorry, הגבהה hagbahah works in all places, meaning it works in רשות
הרבים, rishut harabbim, it works in רשות rishut in the even on
the property of the person who's selling the object. So if it
works in all places it should work also on all objects and
it can even work on a slave even though normally it's only
חזקה chazakah that works on a slave, הגבהה hagbahah would also work.
Now we're going to bracket that debate about הגבהה hagbahah on a
slave, that's not our interest. Our interest is why is this a
חזקה chazakah on a slave? Until now we've been defining... What's a
חזקה? chazakah? When you improve the object. So, if you were to
use that logic by a slave, you would only do a חזקה
chazakah on a slave when you would improve the slave. So, some
of the ראשונים Rishonim say you could think of an example like
that. Let's say I gave him a haircut. You know, let's say
I did something to actually, you know, I got, you know, gave
him a manicure. Whatever. I did something that I improved the slave.
Okay, that could be possible, but that's not what we're having here.
What we're having here is that I benefited from the slave. Slaves
improving the master? Exactly. Slave should be קונה koneh the master. So
that's the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that you see from
here that a, you see from the חזקה chazakah of slaves that
we need to broaden our understanding of חזקה. chazakah. חזקה chazakah is
not just when you improve the land, but when you derive benefit
from the land, which is much more similar to the חזקה chazakah
of ג' שנים, gimmel shanim, you harvest the fruits. So now the
question would be, whoa, wait a minute, so you telling me that
if I just go into the land and I pick the apples,
that's going to be a חזקה? chazakah? And the answer is no.
It was very intentional that the example was that you put a
mattress down on the land because there you are deriving benefit directly
from the land itself. If I pick apples off the tree, right,
the land is down here, the tree is over there, you know,
I'm getting benefit from the tree. It's true the tree is growing
from the land and the land allowed the fruit to grow and
I'm getting, but that's not directly from the land itself. Now, you
could even say, let's say I don't know, but how about if
I've got wheat growing and I harvest or tomato, you know, and
I harvest them? But nevertheless, the act of getting benefit is when
the stuff is harvested and I'm putting it in my mouth and
then I'm benefiting from the fruit. It has to be that the
act is directly from the land. So, but let's say, so for
example, here would be an example, let's say I go into the
land and we're going to have like a little, we're going to
do a foot, have a football game. Okay, we're going to play
a little pickup, you know, baseball or whatever and we use this
nice empty plot of land. That would be an example because I'm
directly benefiting from that, you know, from the ground itself. The act
of הנאה hana'ah is directly in relationship to the ground. Whereas when
I pick fruit, it's you know, I've harvested it and then I
get my benefit after. So and therefore, some ראשונים Rishonim say that
all these cases of the slaves, I was directly interacting with the
slave. But let's say, for example, the slave, I, here's a הפקר
hefker slave and I want to do a חזקה chazakah on it
or whatever, or you're selling me your slave and I say, oh
great, you know what, could you go ahead and like write me
a letter to handle some of my correspondence here, take dictation? And
then whatever, and he goes ahead and he writes the letter and
he sends it off. That wouldn't work because I am, the benefit
is, right, that he's like produced this letter, it's sort of like
the fruit of a tree, and I'm getting this letter sent off
to whatever. Or I say, yeah slave, go work in my field,
go pick the berries. That wouldn't work because I'm not directly deriving
the benefit. All of these cases were a direct interaction with the
slave that I, you know, my body, my person was directly benefiting
from, from the slave himself. So it's a חידוש, chiddush, but we,
and you know, but we, but it's, we have to, we have
to like keep it within a certain narrow boundaries because otherwise it
becomes exactly identical to the חזקה chazakah of ג' שנים, gimmel shanim,
at least in terms of, you know, the sense of the harvesting
of the fruit. Yes. Would, would, could you say something about the,
this is a foundational concept of the סוגיא sugya on נכסי הגר
הפקר. nichsei hager hefker. Yeah. I find that as very troubling. Is
there anything you have to say to contextualize it or to, it's
as troubled as it is very troubling, right? Maybe I should, but
I've been like inured to it. I mean, the גר ger could
pass on his property if he had children after he converted. But
if he had no children, then he has no, there's nobody he's
considered related to. He has no family. I understand that. It's just
like even based on הלכות אבילות hilchos aveilus issue, in other words
he's cut off from, right. I mean, I understand there's like, yeah,
there is this poignancy about the idea. If what you're trying to
get at is that even after he converts and he's welcomed into
the Jewish family and we have all these מצוות mitzvos of אהבת
הגר ahavas hager and to make it, you know, to make them
feel like a part, you know, a full member, not just to
make, to create a reality of a full membership, at the end
of the day he doesn't have relatives, you know, and that's expressed
and his sort of outsider status gets expressed when he dies and
nobody, so that's very true. I think that's why all those, that's
why there's all those heightened מצוות mitzvos by a גר ger because
at the end of the day, you know, he doesn't have the
family connections. He is cut off from his birth family and so
on. I mean, you know, and so there's, there is that real
aloneness you're potential, you know, for the גר. ger. That's that's. No,
I'm glad that you mentioned that. Yeah. Okay, so now. Was it
possible for him to bequeath his property to, oh he can, sure,
he can write a will. He can write a will, yeah. This
is when he didn't. He died intestate. You like that I know
that word? Yes. So if some, if someone dies and has no
heirs, no will, no, right, but it's not a גר. ger. So
then you just, so we're all related to everybody else. As long
as there's one other Jew alive, there's somebody who's going to be
able to inherit, right? Might be the hundredth cousin a thousand times
removed, but... He just keep on going through the through the relations
till you find somebody. It tells you on the internet. Yeah, exactly.
All right, so let's just read one more line. But anyway, this
is a big חידוש chiddush that חזקה chazzakah of קניין kinyan works
even to derive benefit, not just to improve, as long as that
is directly derived from the thing itself. Okay, that direct interaction with
the thing itself. אמר רב ירמיה ביראה אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav
Yirmeya Bira'a Amar Rav Yehuda: האי מן דשדא ליפתא—now Hai man d'shada
lifta it can get a little more complicated or whatever, you know—בי
פילי דארעא דגר. bei pilei d'ara d'ger. So we're again with the
land of a גר ger that's הפקר, hefker, and I go and
I drop some seeds into a crevice. So I haven't plowed the
land, I haven't covered it up, I haven't watered it; I just
dropped some seeds. Okay, לא הוי חזקה, lo havi chazzakah, it's not
a חזקה. chazzakah. Why not? I mean, proved it; there's some seeds,
they'll grow. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? בעידנא דשדא לא הוי שבחא. Be'idna
d'shada lo havi shivcha. You haven't improved it. You haven't done anything
to the land yet, meaning if you said that you just have
some seeds that are sitting there. If I actually plowed the land,
watered it, or whatever, I've changed the land in some way. Here,
I just have some seeds that are sitting there. So you say,
השתא דקצמח, hashta d'kasmach, now the seeds begin to grow and then
they become part of the land, and now the land has growing
produce in it. ממילא קצמח, Mimila kasmach, that happens by itself. Okay,
so this is a similar point like, even though it led to
the land being improved, that act narrowly defined hasn't yet transformed the
land and therefore it's not a חזקה. chazzakah. Because it's indirect? Because
it is indirect, because you just put seeds; you didn't actually plow
land over the seeds, you didn't do something to change the land.
It's just seeds sitting in a crevice. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, let's
just read one more case: האי מן דפשח דיקלא אדעתא דדיקלא, Hai
man d'pashach dikla ada'ata d'dikla, so you are pruning a palm tree.
Now the question is—and the palm tree is הפקר hefker or somebody's
trying to sell it to you—are you pruning it for the sake
of improving it? Then it's a חזקה. chazzakah. You did something to
improve. Or are you not interested in improving the palm tree; you're
just trying to get the palm branches to use for סכך schach
or firewood? So if you do it אדעתא דדיקלא ada'ata d'dikla to
improve the palm tree, קני, kani, that's a חזקה. chazzakah. אדעתא דחיותא,
Ada'ata d'chiyusa, you do it for your animals because you're going to
feed them I guess the palm branches, לא קני, lo kani, it
doesn't work. Because even though it's similar to the idea before, you
physically did something that improved it, but you weren't doing it with
the right intent. It wasn't in your mind an act of improving
and therefore it was not an act of חזקה. chazzakah. Now היכי
דמי, heichi dami, how do you know which is which? שקל מהאי
גיסא ומהאי גיסא, Shakal mehai gisa u'mehai gisa, if when you're cutting
off the branches you're doing it evenly distributed from both sides, אדעתא
דדיקלא, ada'ata d'dikla, then we see that you're concerned about the palm
tree. Now, it could just be you don't want to ruin it,
but we're going to be willing to interpret that since in reality
you did improve it as that that was your intention. But כולא
מחד גיסא, kula m'chad gisa, but if you're doing it all from
one side, which is not good for the tree—it's maybe good for
you but not good for the tree—אדעתא דחיותא ada'ata d'chiyusa and therefore
it is not going to be a חזקה. chazzakah. And we'll continue
with similar cases like this tomorrow about acts of חזקה chazzakah that
it's not enough that in practice they improve the thing, but they
have to be done with that intention, that type of an act
that's made for improving the thing.